Guide to the Cornell Woolrich papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Cornell Woolrich Papers,
1958-1964
Woolrich, Cornell, 1903-1968.
1.5 linear feet (3 document boxes)
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
MS#1379
4079630
This collection contains primarily articles and manuscripts by the crime writer Cornell Woolrich.
Biographical Note
Cornell George Hopley-Woolrich was born on December 14, 1903 in New York City to Genero and Claire (neé Attalic) Hopley-Woolrich. In 1907 the family moved to Mexico and Genero and Claire divorced soon after. Cornell stayed with his father in Mexico for the duration of his childhood. As a teenager, he returned to the United States and lived with his mother, his aunt, and his grandfather on West 113th street. Cornell attended DeWitt Clinton High School and went on to attend Columbia University. He would have graduated in 1925, but dropped out his senior year.
Upon leaving school, Woolrich had a brief marriage to Gloria (Violet Virginia) Blackton. Woolrich befriended Blackton and her sister, Marion. After a few short dates, they married on December 6, 1930. A month later, Woolrich disappeared. While he was gone Gloria Blackton discovered his diary and realized that he had been having daily affairs with men throughout their marriage. She quickly divorced him. Woolrich moved back in with his mother and lived with her in the Hotel Marseilles until she died in 1957.
Although he was a guarded and mysterious individual, Woolrich was also a prolific author writing crime and suspense novels and short stories. Many of his works were adapted into films, radio and television plays. He is perhaps most known for his 1942 short story "It Had to be Murder" which was adapted into the Hitchcock directed classic, Rear Window. Woolrich also wrote under the pen name of William Irish.
He continued to write his whole life, however, he became even more of a recluse after his mother died. Woolrich stayed in his hotel room until he died in 1968. There is very little information about his personal life and the information that exists may or may not be true. Woolrich wrote an autobiography (unpublished), yet he sensationalized much of it and in some cases fabricated complete parts of it.
Scope and Content
The bulk of the collection consists of drafts of articles, manuscripts, and plays. There is also a small amount of correspondence and personal items.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into two series.
Series I: Subject Files, 1934-1968
Series II: Writings, 1937-1960
Subjects
Irish, William, 1903-1968; Woolrich, Cornell, 1903-1968; Authors, American.; Crime writing.; Gay authors.; Recluses and authors.; Short stories.; Autobiographies.; Novels.; Scripts.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located on-site.
Bequest of Cornell Woolrich, 1971, 1972
Purchase, 2010
Selected Related Material at Columbia
Frederic Dannay Papers, 1920-1982 Columbia University, Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Series I: Subject Files, 1934-1968
  This small series holds correspondence between Cornell Woolrich and his friend William Thailing. The letters span the bulk of Woolrich's life. Of interest are several cancelled checks made out to Woolrich as payment for twelve stories, including his first story in a pulp magazine.
  - Checks, 1934-1940 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1952-1958, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Last Will and Testament, 1961-1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Dodd, Mead, and Co. Correspondence and Contracts, 1956-1958 (Box 1)
- Series II: Writings, 1937-1960
  Series II contains drafts of several novels, plays, and a run of short stories. There are also portions of Woolrich's unpublished "autobiography."
  - Blues of a Lifetime
    - "Remington Portable NC69411," undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "The Poor Girl," undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Even God Felt the Depression" and "President Eisenhower's Speech," undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "The Maid Who Played the Races," undated (notes) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cover Charge, undated (play) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hotel Room, undated, (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 9 to 10)
  - I Was Waiting for You
    - "I Was Waiting for You," undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - "New York Blues" and "Two Lives," undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Into the Night--Notes, 1950s (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Into the Night--Draft, 1950s (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - King Features Syndicated Articles
    - "The Murderer's Story," 1937 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - "Endicott's Girl," 1938 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - "Murder Does Its Homework," 1941 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "Double-Life," 1943 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "Death Wins the Sweepstakes," 1947 October 6 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "Mystery in Room 913," 1947 October 13 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Death Holds the Downbeat," 1947 November (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Accessory to Murder," 1948 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "The Case of the Body in Grant's Tomb," 1949 January (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - "Case of the Lying Son," 1949 November (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "Murder before the Camera," 1955 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - "Murder in the Dark Blue Night," 1956 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - "The Corpse in the Statue of Liberty," 1957 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - The Loser, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous Fragments, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - The Moon of Montezuma, [1949-1960] (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Night Has a Thousand Eyes--Part I, 1940s (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Night Has a Thousand Eyes--Part II, 1940s (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Somebody Else's Life, 1958 (television play) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Wardrobe Trunk, 1958 (radio play) (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Waltz into Darkness
    - Part I, 1940s (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Part II, 1940s (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Part III, 1940s (Box 3, Folder 7)